Guide to the Marjorie Frye Gutheim papers, 1909-1971 MVC0060.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Marjorie Frye Gutheim papers
1946-1971
1965-1969
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gutheim, Marjorie F.
MVC0060.MS
4.5 Linear Feet 7 grey boxes and 1 flat box
Marjorie Frye Gutheim (1916-2005) taught at Mount Vernon Seminary from 1945-1969 (subjects included U.S. History, International Relations, and Religion). She also served as dean of the Seminary from 1962 until 1969, when the school closed its 93-year-old girls' seminary. This collection contains materials from 1956-1969 and includes teaching materials (syllabi, exams, lecture notes), clippings, correspondence, programs, and publications.
Box 7
Box 6
Box 5
Flat box 8
Box 1
Box 4
Box 2
Box 3
Biographical Note
Marjorie Frye Gutheim (1916-2005) began teaching at Mount Vernon Seminary in 1945, and served as dean from 1962 until 1969, when the school closed its 93-year-old girls' seminary.
Gutheim was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts on January 2, 1916. Gutheim's father, Herman Gutheim, was chief of the Cambridge Fire Department. She graduated from Radcliffe College in 1927 with an A.B. in History, Harvard Graduate School of Education in 1938 with a M.A. in Teaching, and Columbia University in 1955 with a Ph.D. in American History. After working several years as a secretary at Christ Church in Cambridge, Gutheim began her teaching career at Mount Vernon Seminary in 1945. Course subjects included U.S. History, International Relations, and Religion. Once the school closed in 1969, she returned to Cambridge and became associate editor at the Massachusetts Historical Society (MHS). Some of her notable accomplishments as editor included trasncribing the Winthrop papers and creating a 20-volume index to the MHS proceedings. Gutheim died on December 3, 2005 and is buried at Mount Auburn Cemetery.
The Gutheim Family Papers, which cover the lives of both Herman and Marjorie, are stored at the Cambridge Historical Society.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains teaching materials (syllabi, exams, lecture notes), clippings, correspondence, programs, and publications pertaining to Marjorie Frye Gutheim's tenure at Mount Vernon Seminary as a member of the faculty, and later as dean. These materials date from 1956-1969. Teaching subjects include U.S. history, international relations, and religion. Mount Vernon Seminary and College subjects include Alumnae Bulletin clippings, chapel services, commencements, Diamond Jubilee, the Friends of Mount Vernon Seminary, publications, and special events (dedication ceremonies, performances, reunions, etc.).
Acquistion Information
Gift of Cambridge Historical Society, September 2010 (Accession MVC0060.MS).
Organization
The collection is organized into two series: Mount Vernon Seminary and Teaching Materials.
Series are arranged alphabetically.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
8281869
Bib # 8281869
Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
- Mount Vernon Seminary, 1945-2002; 1946-1969; Series 1; Gutheim, Marjorie F.; 0.5 Linear Feet (Flat box 8, Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes Alumnae Bulletin clippings, chapel service programs, publications on Mount Vernon, programs of events held at Mount Vernon Seminary (commencements, dedications, reunions, etc.), newspaper clippings, Cum Laude Society, correspondence, receipts, and information on the class of 1969. The materials date from 1946 to 1969.
  Organization
  Arranged alphabetically. Contents within each folder arranged chronologically. Oversized photographs placed at end of collection in box 8.
  Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
  - Alumnae Bulletin Clippings, 1953-1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapel Services, 1946-1968; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1969, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Commencements, 1946-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and Receipts, 1965-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cum Laude Society, 1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Events Held at Mount Vernon, 1946-2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History of Mount Vernon Seminary, Academic Calendars, Faculty Lists, and Student Lists, 1945-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings about Mt. Vernon Seminary, 1945-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Performance Programs, 1946-1947; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Publications on Mount Vernon Seminary, 1946-1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Aeriel Photo of Mt. Vernon Seminary, undated; Series 1 (Flat box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mt. Vernon Class of 1966 Photograph, Series 1 (Flat box 8, Folder 2)
  - Photographs - Students on Boat Cruise, circa 1960-1970; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Teaching Materials, 1909-1969; 1956-1969; MVC0060.MS, Series 2; Gutheim, Marjorie F. (Box 3, Box 2, Flat box 8, Box 5, Box 4, Box 1, Box 7, Box 6)
  Collection includes teaching materials for courses in U.S. History, International Relations, and Religion (Old and New Testament). Materials date from 1956-1969.
  Arranged alphbetically by topic. Oversized teaching maps placed at end of collection in Box 8.
  Mount Vernon Seminary
  - American Painting--Teaching Materials, 1948-1968; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ancient History--Exams, 1945-1948; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ancient History--Teaching Materials, 1933-1934; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Architecture (17th and 18th Century)--Teaching Materials, 1953-1965; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - European History--Exams, 1943-1963; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - India, Pakistan, and Himalayan Countries--Teaching Materials, 1965-1968; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - International Relations--Exams and Assignments, 1962-1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Relations--Miscellaneous Materials, 1968-1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International Relations--Teaching Materials [1/2], 1963-1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Relations--Teaching Materials [2/2], 1956-1968; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Literature--Teaching Materials, 1959-1960; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Middle East, 1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Religion 103--Notes and Assignments, 1965-1966; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Religion--Charts and Maps, undated; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Religion--New Testament Assignments and Exams [1/2], 1950-1961; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Religion--New Testament Assignments and Exams [2/2], 1962-1969; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Religion--New Testament--Magazines, 1951-1961; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Religion--New Testament Notes and Outlines, 1946-1967; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Religion--Old Testament Assignments and Exams, 1952-1961; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Religion--Old Testament Notes, 1956-1967; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Religion--Old Testament--Plays and Pageants, undated; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Religion--Teaching Materials, 1943-1967; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Southeast Asia, 1969; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, 1969; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - United Nations, 1957-1966; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Foreign Policy, 1956-1969; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Government--Exams, 1944-1951; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Government--Teaching Materials, 1951-1968; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - U.S. History--1865 to 1900--Exams, 1954-1968; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - U.S. History--American Civilization [1/2], 1958-1964; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - U.S. History--American Civilization [2/2], 1967-1968; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - U.S. History--Assignments and Exams for Academic Year 1964-1965, Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - U.S. History--Assignments and Materials for Academic Year 1965-1966, Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - U.S. History--Assignments and Materials for Academic Year 1966-1967, Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - U.S. History--Between the World Wars--Exams, 1954-1969; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - U.S. History--Charts and Maps, 1953-1954; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - U.S. History--Civil War and Reconstruction--Exams, 1954-1969; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - U.S. History--College Board Review Exams, 1927-1952; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - U.S. History--Constitution--Exams, 1967; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - U.S. History--Discovery and Exploration to Colonial America--Exams, 1954-1967; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - U.S. History--The Early Republic, 1789-1820--Exams, 1954-1967; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - U.S. History--Exams and Assignments [1/4], 1929-1955; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - U.S. History--Exams and Assignments [2/4], 1956-1963; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - U.S. History--Exams and Assignments [3/4], 1964-1967; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - U.S. History--Exams and Assignments [4/4], 1968-1969; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - U.S. History--Field Trip, 1956-1957; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - U.S. History--Graphs, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - U.S. History--Imperialism, Progressive Era, and World War I--Exams, 1954-1969; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - U.S. History--Jackson and Expansion--Exams, 1954-1966; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - U.S. History--News of the Nation, 1953; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - U.S. History--Revolution to Confederation--Exams, 1954-1966; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials, 1962-1968; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--American Revolution [1/2], 1952-1953; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--American Revolution [2/2], 1952-1960; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Civil War and Reconstruction [1/3], 1909-1961; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Civil War and Reconstruction [2/3], 1960-1961; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Civil War and Reconstruction [3/3], 1927-1960; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Colonial America [1/2], undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Colonial America [2/2], 1928-1962; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Discovery and Exploration, undated; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Early 20th Century, 1946-1967; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Federal Period [1/2], 1937-1964; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Federal Period [2/2], 1949-1964; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Gilded Age and Industrial Development, 1953; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--Jacksonian Democracy and Expansion, 1917; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - U.S. History--Teaching Materials--New Deal to 1960s, 1943-1968; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - U.S. History--WWII to the 1960s--Exams, 1957-1967; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Teaching Materials--Oversized Maps, undated; Series 2 (Flat box 8, Folder 3)